Finding Aid for the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee Records LSC.0107
UCLA Library Special Collections
Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee records
1942-1945
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.0107
5.5 linear feet (11 boxes and 2 oversize boxes)
The Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee (formerly the Citizen's Committee for the Defense of Mexican American Youth) formed in 1942 in reaction to the indictment of 22 young men for murder. 12 defendants were convicted of first degree murder. The Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee raised funds to appeal the case and roused public opinion through education and publicity programs. In 1944 the original judgment was overturned. The collection contains correspondence, publications, publicity materials, radio scripts, office records, a transcript of the Sleepy Lagoon trial, and research materials including articles about Mexicans and Mexican Americans in Los Angeles. Portions of the collection are in Spanish.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alice Greenfield McGrath, 1945.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID:9929769213606533
History
The Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee (first known as the Citizens' Committee for the Defense of Mexican American Youth) was organized in October 1942 in response to the indictment of 22 young men for murder; all defendants but one were Mexican American; 12 defendants were convicted of first degree murder by Superior Court of Los Angeles County; Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee raised funds for the appeal of the case and roused public opinion through education and publicity programs; judgments and decisions of the lower court were reversed by the District Court of Appeal of the state of California, 2nd Appellate District, October 4, 1944.
Additional Historical Narrative
In August 1942, 22 defendants, all Mexican Americans but one, were indicted by the grand jury of Los Angeles county for the murder of José Diaz, whose death occurred at a party on the Williams ranch in the city of Los Angeles near a little pond called the Sleepy Lagoon. 12 were convicted of first degree murder by the Superior Court of Los Angeles County; the case was appealed to the District Court of Appeal of the state of California, 2nd Appellate District, where the judgments and decisions of the lower court were reversed (October 4, 1944).
The Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee (first known as the Citizens' Committee for the Defense of Mexican-American Youth) was organized around October 1942, and dissolved January 1, 1945. It raised funds for the appeal of the boys' case and roused public opinion to their cause through an educational and publicity program. The Archive was transferred to the Library by Alice Greenfield, Executive Secretary of the committee, 1945.
Scope and Content
Collection contains correspondence, publications, publicity materials, radio scripts, office records, petitions, and research materials of the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee. Research materials include articles about Mexicans and Mexican Americans in Los Angeles. Also includes an article from Guy Endore. A transcript of the Sleepy Lagoon trial is also in the collection.
Extended Scope and Content Note
Materials in the archive include the following categories:
a) Committee publicity
b) Publications
c) Correspondence
d) Office materials
e) Petitions
f) Materials concerning the defendants, including Guy Endore's article, from Hoy (August to September 1944)
g) Materials collected by the committee concerning the Mexican minority
h) Miscellaneous materials collected by the committee
i) Legal materials including a transcript of the appeal trial.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Publicity.
Publications.
Correspondence.
Office Materials and Records.
Materials concerning defendants.
Materials regarding minorities, especially Mexican minority problems in Los Angeles.
Miscellaneous materials concerning minorities, labor, etc.
Photographic plates and newspaper mats.
Transcript of trial.
Legal documents.
Scrapbooks.
Miscellaneous items.
Boxes 1-12 of the collection have been copied onto 8 reels of microfilm.
Related Material
The Education of Alice McGrath [oral history transcript] / Alice Greenfield McGrath, interviewee. Center for Oral History Research interview, 1987. [Call number: 300/269]. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Alice Greenfield McGrath Papers ( Collection 1490 ). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
S. Guy Endore Papers ( Collection 279 ). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee Records, 1942-1945 (59 items).
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee Records, 1942-1945 (104 items).
Civil Rights--California--Los Angeles.; Los Angeles (Calif.)--Race relations.; Mexican-American youth--California--Los Angeles.; Sleepy Lagoon Trial, Los Angeles, Calif., 1942-1943.; McGrath, Alice, 1917-2009; Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee (Los Angeles, Calif.) -- Archives
- Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee's Publicity Regarding Case
  General note
  Available on microfilm reel 1.
  - News releases. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Mimeographed copies.
    - Letter, 1944 March 1 to Parole Board, San Quentin, California (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - News release: Sleepy Lagoon case and the press, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Upper left hand corner: Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee, Carey McWilliams National Chairman.
    - News release: reasons for the convictions in the Sleepy Lagoon case, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - News release: telegram from Latin American labor delegates stating support of the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee, 1944 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      The Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee releases the telegram sent by 14 Latin American deleagets of the International Labor Organization Conference held in Philadelphia, Pa.
    - News release: support for the Sleepy Lagoon defendants and appeal of the trial (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - News release: the CIO supports the Sleepy Lagoon case defendants, 1944 September 9 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - News release: brief submitted to the Board of Prison Terms and Parole at San Quentin on behalf of the Sleepy Lagoon defendants, 1944 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Katz, Gallagher and Margolis prepare oral arguments for the appeal in the Sleepy Lagoon case, 1944 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee claims a real victory with the announcement of the parole of nine of the defendants, 1944 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Hollywood benefit buffet to be held in support of the Sleepy Lagoon defendants, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Sponsors of the benefit buffet include Vincent Price, John Garfield Anthony Quinn, Katherine Locke and Elia Kazan, among others.
    - Sleepy Lagoon case dismissed on October 23, 1944 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Memorandum, 1943 November 4 to Charles Ellis, Labor Herald (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Social conditions of Mexican American youth (Box 1, Folder 1)
      1943 March 2
    - We have just begun to fight (draft), 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Citizens' Committee for the Defense of Mexican American Youth deplore attacks against Mexican youth, 1943 June (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Press telegram, the Daily People's World, San Francisco, Calif. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee to be abolished, 1944 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - News release: Manuel Delgado is the first Sleepy Lagoon defendant released from prison (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Manny Delgado is the first of the Sleepy Lagoon defendants to be paroled from prison.
    - News release: Hollywood fund raiser held to benefit the Sleepy Lagoon defense, 1943 December (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Benefit held December 12,1943 at the Mocambo in Hollywood with Anthony Quinn was the keynote speaker. In attendance were Katherine DeMille, John Garvey and Gene Kelly among other notable Hollywood stage, screen and radio writers, directors and actors.
  - News releases. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Preliminary drafts and carbon copies.
  - Publicity stories concerning case. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    In English.
    [Empty/Filmed empty]
  - Publicity stories written by Alice Greenfield., (3 items). (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Shipyard worker Eliseo Hernandez sells out copies of the pamphlet "The Sleepy Lagoon Case", 1943 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Eliseo Hernandez walked into the SLDC office and asked for copies of the pamphlet to sell. In a short time he was selling more copies than had been previously sold.
    - On October 21 the first brief will be filed with the appellate court in the Sleepy Lagoon case, 1943 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - What comes next for the Sleepy Lagoon boys?, 1944 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Greenfield writes of the hopelessness and anger the "boys" initially felt and how that changed to hope and strength as the work of their supporters paved the way for their release.
  - Publicity stories., (2 items). (Box 1, Folder 5)
    In Spanish.
    - Straight wire press release: Veredicto del caso de la Laguna Dormida revocada = Sleepy Lagoon case verdict reversed, 1944 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Informe rendido por los Ciudadanos del Comité de Defensa de la Juventud Mexico-Americana, 1943 or 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - El Comité de la Laguna Dormida aclama la decisión de la corte de apelación, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      The Sleepy Lagoon Defense Commitee hails the appellate court decision on the Sleepy Lagoon case.
  - Radio scripts. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Our Daily Bread"., broadcasted May 24, 1944; (4 items).
      - Our Daily Bread radio script, May 5, 1943: the Sleepy Lagoon case (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Van Dycke interviews labor leader Marty on the issues of the case. Our Daily Bread, Radio Department of the Los Angeles CIO Council. KPAS 1110 on the dial.
    - Al Jarvis Show., broadcasted September 22, 1944; (2 items).
      - Radio script for the Al Jarvis show with guest Guy Endore, 1944 September 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        On the Al Jarvis radio show, KFWB, Endore discusses the case and the work of the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee and National Chairman Carey McWilliams. His research into the case led to his book "The Sleepy Lagoon Mystery."
    - Radio script for show with three of the Sleepy Lagoon boys on the day of their release, 1944 October (Box 1, Folder 6)
      On CIO radio program, Partlow gives an introductory background on the facts of the case and then lets the boys speak.
    - Our Daily Bread script, February 18, 1944, Albee Slade, commentator, 1944 February 18 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Our Daily Bread, Radio Department of the Los Angeles CIO Council.
  - Texts of speeches. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Four speeches, including text and outline for speech by Josefina Fierro de Bright, National Secretary Spanish Speaking People's Congress.
  - Publicity work with labor unions., (23 items, including some duplicates). (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes petitions, resolutions, form letters, carbon copies, holograph materials and pamphlets.
    - Letter, 1943 April 30, Los Angeles, Calif. to all State CIO Local Unions (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Letter on Committee letterhead and signed by Chairman J.L. Marty asking unions for their support and donations to the Sleepy Lagoon defense fund. Officers of the Committee are listed across the top of the page and sponsors are listed at the bottom of the page.
    - Los Angeles CIO Council's statement on recent race riots here, 1943 June 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - California CIO Council Resolution in support of the appeal of the Sleepy Lagoon trial, 1943 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Concurred in by the California CIO Council Executive Committee in meeting April 3-4, 1943 held in Los Angeles, Calif.
  - Publicity regarding defense committee publications., (10 items, some duplicates). (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Guy Endore's Sleepy Lagoon Mystery, and also including clippings, form letters, etc.
  - Publicity photographs. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Photos mainly of "the boys."
    - Henry Leyvas at Los Angeles County Jail, 1943 or 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Gus Zamora at Los Angeles County Jail, 1943 or 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Jack Melendez at Los Angeles County Jail, 1943 or 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ysmael "Smiles" Parra and family, 1943 or 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Photograph of Parra, his wife and child on the day of his transfer to Chino Prison.
    - Sleepy Lagoon defendants greeted by supporters on the day of their release, 1944 October (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Photograph taken in lobby of Los Angeles County Jail. In the extreme right hand corner o photograph is Sleepy Lagoon trial defense attorney Ben Margolis.
    - Sleepy Lagoon defendants and Alice McGrath with defense attorney Ben Margolis, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Photograph taken in attorney Margolis' office. The following signed their names above their images, l-r: Angel Padilla, Gus Zamora, J.J. Melendez, Hank Ynostroza, Chepe Ruíz.
    - Sleepy Lagoon defendants leaving Hall of Justice, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ysmael Parra, Gus Zamora and John Matuz with family members, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Standing, l-r: Ysmael Parra holding daughter, Gus Zamora, Matuz and grandmother Mrs. Acuña; sitting, l-r: Delia Parra and a Matuz female cousin. Photograph taken in Chino.
    - Al Jarvis, Henry Ynostroza and Guy Endore, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      L-r: Jarvis, Ynostroza, Endore at the microphone at radio station KFWB when Endore was a guest speaker on the Jarvis program.
    - Sleepy Lagoon defendants boxing in San Quentin, 1943 or 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      l-r: Chepe Ruíz, Bobby Telles, Manny Delgado, Smiles Parra, and Henry Ynostroza with boxing coach.
    - Sleepy Lagoon defendants playing basketball in San Quentin, 1943 or 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Lions basketball team, San Quentin, 1943 or 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Jack Melendez in San Quentin, 1943 or 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Gus Zamora and Johnny Matuz, 1943 or 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Zamora and Matuz at Chino Honor Prison.
    - Bobby Telles with band at Club Azteca, San Quentin, 1944 or 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Bobby Telles playing with quintet at "Club Azteca" in San Quentin. Inscribed in upper right hand corner: "To Alice a cool chick From Bobby Telles Club Azteca."
    - Mrs. Leyvas, 1943 or 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      The mother of Henry Leyvas.
    - Gus Zamora, "Smiles" Parra and Johnny Matuz at Chino prison, 1943 or 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      l-r: Zamora, Parra, Matuz.
    - José"Chepe" Ruíz and Manuel "Manny" Delgado with baseball teammates, 1943 or 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Chepe Ruíz and Manny Delgado posing with prison baseball All Stars.
    - Manuel and Peggy Delgado, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Photograph taken in Chino; cropped for editing on both left and right sides.
    - Basketball players at San Quentin, 1943 or 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Some of the Sleepy Lagoon defendants on the "Lions" basketball team, San Quentin.
  - Miscellaneous publicity., (11 items). (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Program for a pan America, Daily News - clippings.
  - Publicity fragments., (12 items). (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee's Publications
  Available on microfilm reel 2.
  - Appeal News., (April 7, 1943 to March 4, 1944) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Complete file: vol.1 no.1-vol.2 no.6.
    - The Appeal News, 1943 April 7 to 1944 March 4 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      This comprises the complete run of the newletter which was sent to the defendants in the Sleepy Lagoon case and supporters of their defense.
      Name of the committee changed in mid-September 1943.
  - Appeal News., Duplicates. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Printed publications. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Including the Sleepy Lagoon Case (3 copies), Sleepy Lagoon Mystery (3 copies), Sleepy Lagoon Case-Pageant of Prejudice (2 copies).
    - The Sleepy Lagoon case: with a forward by Orson Welles, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Introduction by Marion Bachrach, Executive Secretary, Council for Pan American Democracy.
    - We have just begun to fight!, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Facts of the case are presented after the conviction of the Sleepy Lagoon case defendants.
    - ¡Nuestra lucha apenes [sic] ha comensado!, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Spanish translation of the pamphlet "We have just begun to fight!"
    - Victory for democracy, 1944 October (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Endore writes on the justice finally served with the reversal of the convictions in the Sleepy Lagoon case.
    - Conspiración racial al descubierto en el caso de la "Laguna del Sueño", 1943 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Introduction by Orson Welles.
    - The Sleepy Lagoon case: pageant of prejudice, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    1. Sleepy Lagoon Mystery
    2. Sleepy Lagoon Case
    3. Sleepy Lagoon Case-Pageant of Prejudice by Alice Greenfield.
  - Miscellaneous publications., (7 items, all in triplicate). (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Victory in the Sleepy Lagoon case = Gran victoria en el caso Laguna Dormida, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - This is the story of a crime, 1944 January 29 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee advertisement originally placed in the Los Angeles Daily News and reprinted as a flyer. Provides a background of the case and solicits donations for the defense.
  - Excerpts of Appellate decision., (6 copies). (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Excerpts from the decision of the Second District Court of Appeal of the State of California in the Sleepy Lagoon case; entered October 4, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Excerpts from the appellate court decision which over turned the convictions in the Sleepy Lagoon case.
- Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee's Correspondence
  - Form letters. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Excerpts from a letter written by Manuel Reyes, San Quentin, 1943 April 28 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Reyes writes of doing his part to contribute to the war effort in spite of being in prison.
    - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to supporters of the Sleepy Lagoon case defendants, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Letter written by McGrath, Executive Secretary of the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee, asking supporters to help fight the slander and racism of the press, especially of the Los Angeles Times newspaper.
      Along the left side are listed the officers and sponsors of the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee.
    - Urgent!, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Request for signatures on the petition to Attorney General Kenney calling for the release of the Sleepy Lagoon case defendants.
    - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to trade unionists, 1943 or 1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Letter, on temporary letterhead, from the Chairman and Executive Secretary of the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee. Asks trade unionists to adopt a resolution condemning the injustices in the Sleepy Lagoon case.
    - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee supporters, 1943 or 1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Letter from the National Chariman explaining the reason for sending a copy of "Sleepy Lagoon Mystery" by Guy Endore.
      Along left side are listed the officers and sponsors of the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee.
    - Letter, 1943 December 21, Los Angeles, Calif. to Miss Buck (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Letter from McWilliams explaining why he accepted the position of National Chairman of the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee and asking Miss Buck for her support in the Committee's efforts.
    - Letter, 1943 March 26, Los Angeles, Calif. to Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee members (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Letter on committee letterhead updating members on the status of the case. Announces that Ben Margolis is on board as attorney replacing George Shibley who left for the armed forces. The letter is signed by LaRue McCormick, Secretary.
      Committee officers listed across the top of the page and sponsors are listed at the bottom of the page.
  - Letters to Governor Earl Warren., (2 letters, 3 items). (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Letter to Governor Warren, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Unsigned letter asking Governor Warren to pardon the 17 defendants convicted in the Sleepy Lagoon trial.
    - Letter to Governor Warren, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Unsigned letter requesting that Governor Warren seek the release of the Sleepy Lagoon trial defendants.
  - Correspondence with State Attorney General Robert W. Kenny. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with Mexican Consulate. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence concerning Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee publications. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Order file for Sleepy Lagoon Mystery. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee's Office Materials, Records, etc.
  - Checkbooks with California Bank for Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee (2). (Box 3)
  - Financial statements, accounts, etc., (October 21, 1942 to October 16, 1943) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Expenditures, including Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee Los Angeles Audit Report.
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Including correspondence, minutes of meetings, statement of committee's purpose, etc.
    - Minutes, Conference, Citizens' Committee for the Defense of Mexican-American Youth held March 14, 1943 Belmont Studios, 122 1/2 South Vermont, Los Angeles, 1943 March 14 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Meeting held in order to organize support for the Sleepy Lagoon trial defendants and to organize an appeal of the guilty verdicts.
  - Petitions. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Petition to Governor Earl Warren of California, 1943 or 1943 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Petition to Governor Warren for the reversal of the Sleepy Lagoon convictions. At the bottom of the page is handwritten information for signing and sending in the petition.
    - Petition on the Sleepy Lagoon case to Honorable Robert W. Kenny, Attorney General, State of California, 1943 or 1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Petition asking Attorney General Kenny to examine the facts of the case and set aside all convictions in the Sleepy Lagoon trial.
    - Petition for programs to improve the socio-economic status of Mexican Americans, 1942 November 24 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Petition asking for city, state and federal commitments to programs geared towards helping improve the economic, educational and social status of Mexican Americans.
    - Trip to Folsom and San Quentin, November 7-13, 1943, 1943 November 11 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Alice McGrath reports back to the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Commitee on her visits with the incarcerated Sleepy Lagoon defendants and makes recommendations for actions.
  - Office memo file. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Materials Concerning Defendants
  - Guy Endore's "El Misterio de la Laguna " clipped from Hoy., August 5 to September 30, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence from "the boys" to Alice Greenfield., 1943 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    From San Quentin.
    (Not to be copied)
    - Zoot suiter: drawing, 1943 or 1944 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Drawing of a "zoot suiter" surrounded by hip sayings on Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee letterhead. Sent by Delgado from San Quentin.
    - Letter, 1943 May 16, San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Letter from Parra in San Quentin letting Alice know how the "boys" are doing.
    - Letter, 1944 March 16 to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Letter from Acosta asking Alice for any help she can provide on his case and for word on the "boys up north."